Guide to the Brown Brothers Harriman Records 1696-1973, 1995 (bulk, 1820-1968) MS 78
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Annual Reports and Statements of Condition (1897-1968), 3.125 Linear feet (7.5 document boxes, 2 oversize folders)
  Each report provides a snapshot of contemporary business practices as reflected in staffing decisions and expenditures; areas identified for improvement; levels of funding for a variety of activities; and contact with overseas branches, correspondent banks, and customers. They provide internal documentation, at the departmental level, of financial transactions, trends, and decisions reflected in Series III. Financial and Business Records and Series IV. Business Transaction Records.
  Because the firm was a partnership, the Annual Reports are private and confidential, not the published documents required for a publicly held company answerable to shareholders. The Statements of Condition, however, were both printed and submitted to newspapers and summarize the firm's assets and liabilities. These include final printed versions, newspaper clippings from the scrapbooks of Miss Catherine Barrett (see Series VI. Scrapbooks and Collected Material), and annotated working versions showing required changes.
  The Statements of Condition were donated to the Historical Files Library by Deputy Manager Clarence F. von Glahn in 1969.
  The Annual Reports are arranged chronologically, followed by the Statements of Condition in chronological order. The latter were originally housed individually by year in annotated folders. Information from the folders has been photocopied onto acid-free paper and precedes the materials described.
  Two copies each of two advertisements that were the first Brown Brothers Harriman had ever placed in newspapers, which were included with these materials, have been moved to Series VII. Promotional and Press Material.
  - Annual Report 1897: James Brown report (Offsite-box 79, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report 1897: department reports, 1897-1898 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report 1898 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report 1899 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 12)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1900 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 13)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1901 (Offsite-box 79, Folder 14)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1902 (Offsite-box 81, Folder 1)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1903 (Offsite-box 81, Folder 2)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1904 (Offsite-box 81, Folder 3)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1905 (Offsite-box 81, Folder 4)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1906 (Offsite-box 81, Folder 5)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1907 (Offsite-box 81, Folder 6)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1908 (Offsite-box 81, Folder 7)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1909; absences from office May 1 - December 31; dinner accounts (Offsite-box 81, Folder 8)
  - Department reports and managers' comments 1910 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 1)
  - Domestic Bond Department report; miscellaneous orders; dinner account; statement of absences, 1910 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports 1911 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 3)
  - Office orders; dinner account; staff and attendance lists 1911 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 4)
  - Annual reports 1912 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 5)
  - Office orders; attendance; dinner account 1912 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 6)
  - Accounting Department; Managers' report; Statistical Department; memoranda, 1912 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports 1913 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 8)
  - Annual report of Manager; Statistical Department, 1913 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 9)
  - Office orders; attendance; dinner accounts, 1913 (Offsite-box 83, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports 1914 (Offsite-box 83, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, Statistical Department; Managers' report; attendance; dinner money; office instructions, 1914 (Offsite-box 83, Folder 3)
  - Annual departmental reports; managers' report 1913 (Offsite-box 83, Folder 4)
  - Monthly reports of Statistical Department; attendance; dinner money; office instructions; office staff listing, 1915 (Offsite-box 83, Folder 5)
  - Annual departmental reports; Managers' report, 1916 (Offsite-box 83, Folder 6)
  - Departmental memoranda; office staff listing; attendance records; dinner money account; names addded to and taken from salary list, 1916 (Offsite-box 83, Folder 7)
  - Departmental reports 1917 (Offsite-box 84, Folder 1)
  - Managers' report; dinner money account; office instructions; summary of days off and vacations, 1917 (Offsite-box 84, Folder 2)
  - Departmental reports, year 1918 (Offsite-box 84, Folder 3)
  - Annual reports 1918; managers' report (Offsite-box 84, Folder 4)
  - Departmental reports, 1919 (Offsite-box 84, Folder 5)
  - Annual report; index to subjects; dinner money record; insturctions to departments; office staff listing; summary of days off and vacations, 1919 (Offsite-box 84, Folder 6)
  - Departmental reports 1920 (Offsite-box 84, Folder 7)
  - Office manager's report; Stationery Department; attendance record; office staff listing; instructions to the Departments; dinner money record, 1920 (Offsite-box 85, Folder 1)
  - Departmental reports 1921 (Offsite-box 85, Folder 2)
  - Annual report of the office manager; summary of absences; instructions to the Departments; dinner money record; Mr. Blewett's comments on annual reports 1921; office staff listing (Offsite-box 85, Folder 3)
  - Departmental reports 1922 (Offsite-box 85, Folder 4)
  - Annual report of the Office Manager; summary of absences; dinner money record; office staff listing; instructions to Departments, 1922 (Offsite-box 85, Folder 5)
  - Departmental reports, 1923 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 1)
  - Report of the Office Manager; office staff listing; dinner money record; instructions to departments; summary of absences, 1923 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 2)
  - Departmental reports 1924 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 3)
  - Annual report of the Office Manager; dinner money record; office staff, 1924 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 4)
  - Departmental reports 1925; dinner money; office staff listing; annual report of the Office Manager (Offsite-box 86, Folder 5)
  - Departmental reports, 1926 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 6)
  - Annual report of the Office Manager; dinner money record; office staff, 1926 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 7)
  - Departmental reports 1927 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 8)
  - Departmental reports 1928 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 9)
  - Departmental reports 1929 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports: Loan Operations and Travelers' Credit Departments, 1930 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 2)
  - Statements of condition, 1933-1939 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 3)
  - Statements of condition, 1945, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 4)
  - Statements of condition, 1950, 1951, 1953, 1954, 1956 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 5)
  - Statements of condition, 1957-1959 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 6)
  - Statements of condition, 1960-1963 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 7)
  - Statements of condition, 1964-1966, 1968, 1969 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 8)
  - Statements of condition, 1941, 1942, 1944 (Offsite-box OS 8, Folder 14)
- Series III. Financial and Business Records (1880-1934), 1880-1928; 19.8 Linear feet (6 boxes, 12 oversize folders, 45 volumes)
  The series includes ledgers, salary books, customer and partnership accounts, quarterly and annual accounts by location, receipts, legal documents, and statements providing details of accounting practices and both financial transactions and business practices within and external to Brown Brothers Harriman and its preceding component companies.
  The series is arranged in two subseries:
  Subseries A. Ledgers
  Subseries B. Other Financial and Business Records
  The volumes are numbered differently from others in the Records for ease of access, because the ledgers are so physically distinct and unwieldy (see Subseries A. Physical Description note). The ledgers in Subseries A. are numbered consecutively L1-L36; the volumes in Subseries B. continue (with Volume 13) the numbering system from Series I. Historical Files.
  - Subseries A. Ledgers (1880-1893, 1897-1928), 15.8 Linear feet 36 volumes
    Scope and Contents
    The ledgers consist of 36 oversized bound books (see Physical Description note) documenting profit and loss, private accounts, and general ledger entries from Brown Brothers & Co. between 1880 and 1928. Included in these transactions are details of many of the firm's financial activities documented elsewhere in the Records during this time period.
    For ledgers that have an accompanying index, researchers are advised to consult the index first before accessing the ledger, because of the volumes' physical size (see Physical Description note).
    Physical Description
    The ledgers are up to 2 feet high and as wide as 8 inches; the largest volumes weigh close to 25 pounds. They were originally bound in leather and then covered in canvas chemises. Volumes that have separated from their covers have been rehoused in acid-free containers; those that are physically intact have been cleaned and shrink-wrapped.
    - General ledger #2, 1880 (Offsite-box BBH-64, Volume L 1)
    - Index for General ledger #2, 1880 (Offsite-box BBH-59, Volume L 1 Index)
    - General ledger #3, Undated (Offsite-box BBH-60, Volume L 2)
    - Index for General ledger #3, Undated (Offsite-box BBH-59, Volume L 2 Index)
    - General ledger #4, Undated (Offsite-box BBH-61, Volume L3)
    - Index for General ledger #4, Undated (Offsite-box BBH-59, Volume L 3 Index)
    - General ledger #5, 1884 (Offsite-box BBH-62, Volume L 4)
    - Index for General ledger #5, 1884 (Offsite-box BBH-59, Volume L 4 Index)
    - General ledger #6, 1885 (Offsite-box BBH-63, Volume L 5)
    - Index for General ledger #6, 1885 (Offsite-box BBH-59, Volume L 5 Index)
    - General ledger #7 (with index), Undated (Offsite-box BBH-38, Volume L 6)
    - General ledger #8 (with index), 1887 (Offsite-box BBH-37, Volume L 7)
    - General ledger #9, Section 1, folios 500-899, 1888 (Offsite-box BBH-39, Volume L 8)
    - Index for General ledger #9, Section 1, folios 500-899, 1888 (Offsite-box BBH-40, Volume L 8 Index)
    - General ledger #9, Section 2, folios 900-1199, 1888 (Offsite-box BBH-40, Volume L 9)
    - General ledger #10, Section 1, folios 500-899, 1889 (Offsite-box BBH-41, Volume L 10)
    - Index for General ledger #10, Section 1, folios 500-899, 1889 (Offsite-box BBH-42, Volume L 10 Index)
    - General ledger #10, Section 2, folios 900-1199, 1899 (Offsite-box BBH-42, Volume L 11)
    - General ledger #11, Section 1, folios 599-999, 1890 (Offsite-box BBH-43, Volume L 12)
    - Index for General ledger #11, Section 1, folios 599-999, 1890 (Offsite-box BBH-44, Volume L 12 Index)
    - General ledger #11, Section 2, folios 1000-1399, 1899 (Offsite-box BBH-44, Volume L 13)
    - General ledger #12, Section 1, folios 500-999, 1891 (Offsite-box BBH-45, Volume L 14)
    - Index for General ledger #12, Section 1, folios 500-999, 1891 (Offsite-box BBH-46, Volume L 14 Index)
    - General ledger #12, Section 2, folios 1000-1399, 1891 (Offsite-box BBH-46, Volume L 15)
    - Private accounts ledger #1, 1892-1893 (Offsite-box BBH-48, Volume L 16)
    - Index for Private accounts ledger #1, 1892-1893 (Offsite-box BBH-49, Volume L 16 Index)
    - [Private accounts ledger #2], Undated (Offsite-box BBH-47, Volume L 17)
    - Index for [Private accounts ledger #2], Undated (Offsite-box BBH-59, Volume L 17 Index)
    - Private accounts ledger #3, folios 1-499, 1897-1899 (Offsite-box BBH-32, Volume L 18)
    - Private accounts ledger #4, folios 1-499, 1900-1902 (Offsite-box BBH-29, Volume L 19)
    - Private accounts ledger #5, folios 1-499, 1903-1905 (Offsite-box BBH-30, Volume L 20)
    - Index for Private accounts ledger #5, folios 1-499, 1903-1905 (Offsite-box BBH-59, Volume L 20 Index)
    - Private accounts ledger #6, folios 1-399, 1906-1909 (Offsite-box BBH-27, Volume L 21)
    - Private accounts ledger #7, folios 1-399, 1909-1911 (Offsite-box BBH-28, Volume L 22)
    - Private accounts ledger #8 (with index), Undated (Offsite-box BBH-36, Volume L 23)
    - Private accounts ledger #9 (with index), Undated (Offsite-box BBH-35, Volume L 24)
    - Private accounts ledger #10 (with index), Undated (Offsite-box BBH-33, Volume L 25)
    - Private accounts ledger #11 (with index), Undated (Offsite-box BBH-34, Volume L 26)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #1, folios 1-399, 1911-1913 (Offsite-box BBH-31, Volume L 27)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #2, folios 1-399, 1913-1915 (Offsite-box BBH-49, Volume L 28)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #3, folios 1-439, 1915-1916 (Offsite-box BBH-50, Volume L 29)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #3, folios 1-476, 1917-1918 (Offsite-box BBH-52, Volume L 30)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #4, folios 1-444, 1919-1920 (Offsite-box BBH-51, Volume L 31)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #5, folios 1-438, 1921-1922 (Offsite-box BBH-53, Volume L 32)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #6, folios 1-438, 1923-1924 (Offsite-box BBH-54, Volume L 33)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #7. folios 1-440, 1925-1926 (Offsite-box BBH-55, Volume L 34)
    - Profit and loss account ledger #8, folios 1-430, 1927-1928 (Offsite-box BBH-56, Volume L 35)
    - General ledger, 1928-1929 (Offsite-box BBH-57, Volume L 36)
  - Subseries B. Other Financial and Business Records (1898-1934), 4 Linear feet 1 document box, 5 non-document boxes, 12 oversize folders, 9 volumes
    The subseries includes volumes and loose materials that document the financial condition of Brown Brothers & Co., and W.A. Harriman, including ledger sheets, account books, and trial balances; salary books and partnership accounts; documentation of internal business practices including powers of attorney and statements of non-interest by employees in accounts handled by them on behalf of customers; as well as external documents including individual and institutional customers' statements, transit documents, and receipts.
    The specie shipment folders include information on the movement of barrels of gold coins from Brown Brothers & Co. in New York to Brown Shipley & Co. in Liverpool via steamship. This currency transportation, on vessels including those of the White Star, Imlay Imbrie & Co., and Cunard Lines, ensured the correction of account balances between the houses and a more even foreign exchange.
    The Partnership Journal (Volume 18) provides details of the 1926 unlimited liability partnership among W. Averell Harriman, E. Roland Harriman, and G.H. Walker "for the carrying on of a private banking business".
    The statements of non-interest were in brittle wrappers marked "vault deposit", which have been preservation photocopied. Accompanying these records is documentation of other business-related records housed at one time in various company vaults.
    The specie shipment materials consisted of a disbound volume in which were interleaved many loose pages. The latter are now foldered separately and identified by the date of the pages at which they were originally found.
    The 1898 and 1919 unbound materials were originally each collected into cardboard folders. The 1898 materials were not identified further and have been arranged by city of the office or agency that created them. The 1919 materials were organized into folders, the titles of which are retained here, and are ordered by their city of origin. The box numbers are out of order because of the varying sizes of materials.
    The volumes are arranged chronologically.
    - Specie shipments, 1866 May 18 - 1899 February (Offsite-box 87, Folder 9)
    - Specie shipments: loose materials, 1872 July 11 - 1887 September 10 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 10)
    - Specie shipments: separated materials, 1888 December 15 - 1896 February 14; undated (Offsite-box 88, Folder 1)
    - Boston: annual accounts, 1898 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 6)
    - London: annual accounts, 1898 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 7)
    - New York: balance sheets, 1898 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 8)
    - New York: profit and loss statement; general investments, 1898 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 9)
    - Private account; credits issued, all agencies, 1898 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 10)
    - Blank powers of attorney to transfer stock, 1928, 1930 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 2)
    - Statements of non-interest W.A. Harriman & Co., 1928, 1930 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 3)
    - Blank declarations of non-interest signed by Harry L. Wills, James Yuille, Reginald Martine, Harry S. Rhame, Harry A. Stevenson, 1929 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 4)
    - Blank declarations of non-interest for Milton J. Morphett, 1929 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 5)
    - Blank declarations of non-interest signed by Robert Bruel, Elbert Twaddell, Harry L. Wills, Allen D. Hauser, Harold J. Shattuck, 1929 (Offsite-box 88, Folder unknown container)
    - Blank powers of attorney to transfer stock, signed by Cletus H. Ollier, 1929, 1930 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 7)
    - Blank declarations of non-interest signed by John E. Woods, 1930, 1931 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 8)
    - List of items in vault, 1930, 1951 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 9)
    - Blank declarations of non-interest signed by James Yuille, 1931 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 10)
    - Blank declarations of non-interest signed by Reginald Martine, Byron A. LaForge, Elbert A. Twaddell, 1931 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 11)
    - Declarations of non-interest, 1933, 1934 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 12)
    - Declarations of non-interest signed by William Siebel, 1941 (Offsite-box 89, Folder 1)
    - Boston: sundry accounts, 1918 June - 1919 December (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 2)
    - London: trial balances, 1898 April, September (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 3)
    - London: sundry accounts 1919, 1919 March - April (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 4)
    - New York: ledger; investment and private ledger accounts, 1898 (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 5)
    - New York: 1919 quarterly statements of operating expenses, profit and loss, analysis of resources and liabilities, 1919 March - June (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 6)
    - New York: 1920 quarterly summaries of operating expenses, income, condensed, firm investments profit and loss, analysis of resources and liabilities, 1919 June - 1920 September (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 7)
    - New York: 1921 quarterly summaries of operating expenses, income, condensed, firm investments profit and loss, analysis of resources and liabilities, 1921 March - June (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 8)
    - Philadelphia: sundry accounts, 1898 (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 9)
    - Philadelphia: sundry accounts 1919, 1919 January - July (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 10)
    - Philadelphia: 1919 quarterly summaries of operating expenses, income, condensed, analysis of resources and liabilities, 1919 January - 1920 January (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 11)
    - Philadelphia: 1920 quarterly summaries of operating expenses, income, condensed, analysis of resources and liabilities, 1920 July - October (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 12)
    - Philadelphia: 1921 quarterly summaries of operating expenses, income, condensed, analysis of resources and liabilities, 1921 April - July (Offsite-box OS 10, Folder 13)
    - Salary book, 1865-1914 (Offsite-box BBH-2, Volume 13)
    - Salary book, 1866 July - 1927 February (Offsite-box BBH-2, Volume 14)
    - Salary list, 1887-1909 (Offsite-box BBH-2, Volume 15)
    - Customer accounts, 1887-1922 (Offsite-box BBH-2, Volume 16)
    - Salary book, 1899-1913 (Offsite-box BBH-3, Volume 17)
    - Partnership journal, 1926-1931 (Offsite-box BBH-3, Volume 18)
    - Certificates of deposit receipt book, 1926-1934 (Offsite-box BBH-6, Volume 19)
    - Statements due to banks and individuals (W. A. Harriman & Co.), 1927 March - December (Offsite-box BBH-6, Volume 20)
    - Statements due to banks and individuals (W. A. Harriman & Co.), 1928 October - December (Offsite-box BBH-7, Volume 21)
- Series IV. Business Transaction Records (1910-1968), 2.6 Linear feet (3 document boxes, 14 volumes)
  While Series II. Annual Reports and Statements of Condition and Series III. Financial and Business Records document primarily the internal accounting transactions and financial condition of Brown Brothers Harriman's precursor companies, this series documents a few of the firms' external financial activities and interests. It includes records of stocks sold in the Wall & Hanover Street Realty Company; correspondence with individuals and organizations who purchased Russian ruble war loans in 1916, and with the International Bank of Commerce of Petrograd (some of which is in French), which held the bonds; bonds issued for foreign corporations and governments in the period 1925-1930; records of underwriting syndicates for the purchase of stocks and bonds in which Harriman Ripley & Co., Inc., did and did not participate (including some of the bond issues documented in Volumes 22-34) from the late 1920s through the 1940s; minutes of the Finance Committee of Caledonian Insurance Company; and correspondence related to Frederick Dumaine's challenge to the purchase of the Delaware & Hudson Railroad in 1968.
  Volumes 23-34 were bound by the firm and include carbon copies of letters and telegrams, photostats of bond documents, and original printed offerings. Volumes 32 and 33 are identical duplicates.
  The syndicate records consist predominantly of filled out (typed or handwritten) preprinted file cards arranged in tabbed alphabetical order by the name of the company or municipality offering being underwritten. They include details of prices paid, dates of offering and expiration, and selling commissions received.
  The Delaware & Hudson-related correspondence appears to have come from the files of John B. Madden, a Brown Brothers Harriman partner who had served since 1964 as a manager of the Delaware & Hudson Company (a holding entity) and a director of the Delaware & Hudson Railroad Corporation.
  The Wall and Hanover Street Realty Company was constituted after the death of James Brown to capitalize the property on which Brown Brothers & Co.'s headquarters stood, at 59 Wall Street, in order to distribute shares to his many heirs and other parties.
  To finance the enormous debt it had incurred during World War I, the Russian imperial government issued bonds in 1916, some of which which were handled by Brown Brothers on behalf of individual and institutional customers.
  The investment banking firm Harriman Ripley & Co., Inc. (originally called Brown Harriman and Co. but renamed in 1938 to avoid confusion) was formed in 1934 after the Glass-Steagall Act of 1933 mandated the separation of investment and commercial banking activities of individual firms. Its initial officers were four Brown Brothers Harriman partners and associates from National City Bank's securities affiliate.
  Brown Brothers Harriman partner Knight Woolley was a director of Caledonian Insurance Company beginning in the 1930s. He served later as chair of its Finance Committee, to which the bank acted as investment advisor.
  In 1968, Delaware & Hudson Railroad's president and largest individual stockholder, Frederick Dumaine, Jr., unsuccessfully opposed a plan to sell the railroad to the Norfolk & Western Railroad, which move was supported by Delware & Hudson directors including Brown Brothers Harriman partners John B. Madden and E. Roland Harriman. The plan was intitially suggested by the Interstate Commerce Commission in an effort to balance the East Coast rail monopoly occasioned by the previous merger of the Pennsylvania and New York Central Railroads.
  The volumes are arranged chronologically, as are the foldered materials except as noted otherwise here.
  The Russian ruble bond materials are often organized alphabetically within folders by name of correspondent, as noted on the folder labels.